In this video, we're going to talk about
the centripetal force.
But when you hear the word centripetal
force, what do you think about?
Now, before we talk about it, let's go
over
a few things. So, let's say if we have
an object that is moving to the right
and a force is acting on the object in
the same direction as the velocity
vector.
What's going to happen to the object?
If the force and velocity vectors are in
the same direction,
the object's speed will increase. It's
going to speed up.
Now, what if the force vector
is in the opposite direction to the
velocity vector?
In this case, the object
is going to slow down.
Now,
let's say if we have an object moving to
the right, but this time, the force
vector
is going up. It's perpendicular to the
velocity vector.
What's going to happen?
The object, it's not going to speed up
or slow down. Instead, it's going to
turn.
And that's what a centripetal force
does. It causes an object to turn in a
circle.
Now,
centripetal has the keyword centry or
center-seeking. This is a center-seeking
force. And so, the force is always
directed towards the center of the
circle.
And thus, that is a centripetal force.
It's any force that keeps an object
moving in a circle.
Now, the centripetal force is not a
force by itself. In fact, it's caused by
other forces.
So, here's an example. Let's say if we
have a person
and he has a ball attached to a rope
and he's swinging this ball in a circle.
So, what force provides the centripetal
force in this case?
Anytime you have a force acting through
a rope,
what is that force called?
This force is the tension force.
So, in this particular situation,
tension provides the centripetal force.
It keeps the ball moving in a circle.
Now, let me give you another situation.
Let's say if you have a car, which I'm
just going to draw a box,
but this is a car.
And
it's turning
on a road. It's following the curvature
of the road and it's turning.
The fact that it's turning, there's some
force
that it's causing it to turn. Let's say
if it's moving at constant speed and
turn at the same time.
So, there is a centripetal force acting
on this car because it's moving in a
circular path.
What centripetal force, or rather what
other force provides the centripetal
force in this case?
If you see a situation like this,
static friction provides the centripetal
force.
So, if you're dealing with a physics
problem that has a car turning on a road
like this, make sure you set static
friction equal to a centripetal force.
Now, the formula for static friction is
μs times the normal force. It's less
than or equal to this quantity.
And for the centripetal force, it's mv²
/ r.
The normal force on a flat surface is
simply mg.
So, in this case,
we could cancel m
in the expression.
So, for a word problem that involves a
car turning on a road,
you have this expression. The
coefficient of static friction times the
gravitational acceleration is equal to v
squared over r.
And I'm going to post some links in
which you can practice these problems
in another video.
Now, let's say
this is the sun
and
here we have the Earth.
And the Earth is orbiting
the sun.
So, the Earth is moving in a nearly
circular path around the sun, which
means that
there's a force that's acting as a
centripetal force in this case to keep
the Earth moving with a uniform circular
motion.
What force provides the centripetal
force in this case?
The force that keeps the Earth in orbit
around the sun
is the gravitational force.
And so, gravity provides the centripetal
force in this example.
Without gravity, the Earth will fly off
in a tangent away from the sun deep into
outer space.
But, because we have these two forces
that are perpendicular to each other,
the Earth instead turns in a circular
path.
And so, make sure you understand this.
Anytime you have a force that's
perpendicular to the velocity component,
I mean, the velocity vector,
the force
doesn't speed up or slow down the
object. It has no effect on the speed.
If it's perpendicular to the velocity of
the object, the force can only change
its direction.
Now, let's focus on the equation
that relates to the centripetal force
acting on the object. It's mv squared
over r.
So, here's a question for you.
If the mass of the object increases,
what will happen to the centripetal
force?
Will it increase or decrease?
Because the mass is in the numerator of
the fraction,
increase in the mass will increase the
centripetal force.
The same is true for the velocity.
If you increase the speed of the object,
the centripetal force that's needed to
keep the object moving in a circle
must be increased as well.
Otherwise, the object is going to fly
out of the circle.
So, the greater the speed,
the more centripetal force that is
needed to keep the object moving in a
circle.
Now, what about if we increase the
radius of the circle?
What's going to happen to the
centripetal force that is needed to keep
the object moving in a circle?
If you use a wider circle,
the centripetal force that's needed to
keep it in that circle will decrease
because R is in a denominator of the
fraction.
And so, let's focus on questions like
these.
What effect will the following changes
have on the centripetal force acting on
an object?
So, what's going to happen if we double
the mass?
We know the centripetal force will
increase, but by what factor?
Now, the way in which you can get the
answer is as follows.
Everything that doesn't change, replace
it with a one.
Now, because the mass increased by the
factor of two, replace M with two.
V and R we're going to replace it with
one.
So, we get a value of two.
This tells us that the centripetal force
will double
if
we double the mass.
Now, let's move on to part B.
So, what effect will it have on the
centripetal force if the speed is
increased by a factor of two?
So, the mass and the radius doesn't
change, so we're going to replace it
with a one.
But, the speed is doubled, so we're
going to replace it with a two.
Two squared is four. And so, this tells
us that the centripetal force
will increase by a factor of four.
Now, what about part C?
The radius
is decreased by four.
Let's say decreased by a factor of four.
So, what should we do?
M and V doesn't change, so we're going
to replace that with a one.
If the radius is decreased by a factor
of four,
that means that it's 1/4 of its original
value.
So, we have 1 / 1/4, which is four.
If you want to show your work with that,
what you need to do is multiply the top
and the bottom by four.
4 * 1/4 is one. And so, you get four.
Now, what about the last one?
Part D.
What effects
will
tripling the mass, quadrupling the
speed, and cutting the radius in half
have on the centripetal force
acting on the object?
So, all we got to do is plug in these
numbers.
So, we're going to triple the mass,
replace it with a three.
The speed is quadrupled, so we're going
to replace that with a four.
And uh the radius was cut in half, so
let's replace R with 1/2.
So, we have four squared, which is
16. 16 * 3
is 48.
And 48 / 1/2 is the same as 48 * 2.
And so, we get 96.
So, the centripetal force will increase
by a factor of 96 in his case.
And that's basically it for this video.
So, I want to give you a simple
introduction into centripetal force.
Now, for those of you who want actual
harder problems
regarding this topic,
check out the links in the description
section because
I'm going to post some links to other
videos that have more problems on this
topic
and other videos that you might be
interested into.
And when you get a chance, check out my
new physics video playlist because I
have these topics listed in order.
And if you like this video,
don't forget to subscribe to this
channel
for more informational content. So, I do
have other videos on like calculus,
algebra, trig, chemistry,
and other
hard classes that people
have difficulties with in high school
and college.
So, if you need help with those courses,
feel free to check out my channel
and you might find something that could
help you. Thanks again for watching.